{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Cement Kiln is a", "opta": "rotary Kiln", "optb": "tunnel Kiln", "optc": "natural draft furnace", "optd": "batch furnace", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a furnace employing forced draught as compared to induced draught,", "opta": "air is sucked in, so air leaks are more and hence the furnace efficiency is reduced.", "optb": "the fan operates hot and hence blades are liable to corrosion and erosion.", "optc": "positive pressure exists in the furnace.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Regenerators are installed in", "opta": "coke ovens", "optb": "open hearth furnace", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a heat treatment furnace ?", "opta": "Muffle furnace", "optb": "Annealing furnace", "optc": "Reheating furnace", "optd": "Rotary kiln", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ atmosphere is maintained inside an iron blast furnace.", "opta": "Oxidising", "optb": "Reducing", "optc": "Inert", "optd": "Decarburising", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Example of an indirectly heated furnace is", "opta": "hood annealing furnace", "optb": "muffle furnace", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which furnace employs preheating, heating and soaking zones ?", "opta": "Soaking pit", "optb": "Reheating furnace", "optc": "Open hearth furnace", "optd": "Cupola", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Calcination of limestone to produce lime is done in a __________ kiln.", "opta": "tunnel", "optb": "rotary", "optc": "vertical shaft", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thickness of stock does not affect the fuel economy of furnaces, if the material to be heated is of", "opta": "low emissivity", "optb": "high thermal conductivity", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic recuperators compared to metallic recuperators for the same duty", "opta": "are lighter.", "optb": "occupy more space.", "optc": "are less costly.", "optd": "have higher pressure differential between flue gas & air side.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to maintain a reducing atmosphere in a furnace, it should have", "opta": "no O2 in flue gas", "optb": "CO in flue gas", "optc": "high excess air", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the most thermally efficient furnace ?", "opta": "Reheating furnace", "optb": "Reverberatory furnace", "optc": "Rotary kilns", "optd": "Boiler furnace", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat recoverable from flue gases of furnaces depends on the", "opta": "thermal efficiency of furnace.", "optb": "quantity of flue gases.", "optc": "flue gas temperature drop through the furnace.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic recuperators (made of SiC) is economical, only when used for preheating combustion air above __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "250", "optb": "650", "optc": "850", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is a continuous furnace ?", "opta": "Coke ovens", "optb": "Annealing furnace", "optc": "Glass tank furnace", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for preheating combustion air above 650\u00b0C ?", "opta": "Regenerator", "optb": "Metallic recuperator", "optc": "Ceramic recuperator", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Soaking pits are meant for heating steel", "opta": "ingots", "optb": "coils", "optc": "sheets", "optd": "slabs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The purpose of controlling the furnace atmosphere is to prevent surface attack by", "opta": "oxidation/scaling", "optb": "decarburising", "optc": "sulphur penetration", "optd": "either of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal efficiency of a limestone calcination rotary kiln may be around __________ percent.", "opta": "20", "optb": "40", "optc": "65", "optd": "80", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In producer gas making furnace, steam is added along with air to mainly control the", "opta": "fusion of coal ash & clinker formation.", "optb": "C. V. of producer gas.", "optc": "temperature of producer gas.", "optd": "tar content in producer gas.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fuel used in B.F. stove is", "opta": "pulverised coal", "optb": "furnace oil", "optc": "blast furnace gas/mixed gas", "optd": "coke oven gas", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tunnel kilns are usually used for", "opta": "roasting of pyrites.", "optb": "drying/tempering of refractories.", "optc": "reheating of slabs.", "optd": "melting of glass.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of a steel slab reheating furnace (walking beam type) may be about __________ percent.", "opta": "15", "optb": "40", "optc": "70", "optd": "85", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Higher furnace temperature can not be achieved by use of a lean fuel gas in the furnace by", "opta": "increasing the draft in the furnace.", "optb": "preheating the fuel gas.", "optc": "oxygen enrichment of combustion air.", "optd": "preheating the combustion air.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Temperature of a furnace fired with low calorific value fuel gas (i.e. lean gas) can be increased by", "opta": "preheating the combustion air.", "optb": "oxygen enrichment of combustion air.", "optc": "preheating the fuel gas.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic coating material for furnace refractory, which increases its emissivity and thus the radiation heat transfer rate in the furnace, comprises of", "opta": "graphite powder", "optb": "thoria", "optc": "zircon powder", "optd": "beryllium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In reverberatory furnace, charge is heated mainly by", "opta": "conduction.", "optb": "natural convection.", "optc": "radiation of heat from the roof of the combustion chamber.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An example of a periodic furnace is the", "opta": "blast furnace stoves", "optb": "blast furnace", "optc": "coke oven heating chamber", "optd": "rotary kilns", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ostwald charts are meant for", "opta": "computing the excess/deficiency of combustion air.", "optb": "calculation of flue gas temperature.", "optc": "computation of flue gas analysis.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum heat transfer in high temperature furnaces is by", "opta": "conduction", "optb": "convection", "optc": "radiation", "optd": "either (a), (b) or (c); depends on the type of furnace", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a natural draft furnace ?", "opta": "Blast furnace stoves", "optb": "Power plant boilers", "optc": "Sintering furnace", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To reduce the stack loss, heat recovery from flue gas can be done by", "opta": "preheating of cold stock.", "optb": "preheating of combustion air.", "optc": "steam generation in waste heat boilers.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Large tonnage of refractory bricks are dried in a", "opta": "shaft furnace", "optb": "rotary hearth furnace", "optc": "tunnel kiln", "optd": "muffle furnace", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pulverised fuel fired furnaces employ __________ fuel firing.", "opta": "horizontal", "optb": "vertical", "optc": "tangential", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a directly fired furnace ?", "opta": "By-product coke oven", "optb": "Calcination kiln", "optc": "Sintering furnace", "optd": "Open hearth furnace", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reason for excessive clinker formation in gas producers is the", "opta": "use of coal/coke containing a high % of fines and ash.", "optb": "use of fuel having too low an ash fusion temperature.", "optc": "development of hot spots in the fuel bed and an abnormally high rate of gasification.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an additive for flue gases from furnace to reduce its dew-point?", "opta": "Ammonia", "optb": "Fine dolomite", "optc": "Alkaline powders", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acid dew point temperature (ADT) of a flue gas produced by the combustion of a fuel containing 1% sulphur may be about __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "80", "optb": "130", "optc": "180", "optd": "250", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Low stack loss indicates the", "opta": "use of sub-stoichiometric air for combustion.", "optb": "efficient use of fuel.", "optc": "inefficient use of fuel.", "optd": "oxygen enrichment of combustion air.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal efficiency of blast furnace stoves used for heating blast (air) may be about __________ percent.", "opta": "20", "optb": "40", "optc": "60", "optd": "80", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat transfer rate to the stock/charge in the furnace does not depend upon the", "opta": "emissivity of the refactory walls.", "optb": "size of the furance.", "optc": "use of waste heat recovery equipments.", "optd": "thickness of the stock.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coke ovens in steel plant are heated by", "opta": "electricity", "optb": "blast furnace gas/mixed gas", "optc": "coke oven gas", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power required in case of forced draught as compared to induced draught (for the same draught produced) is", "opta": "same", "optb": "less", "optc": "more", "optd": "either more or less; depends on the flue gas density", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Means for giving direction to the circulation of gases in furnaces are", "opta": "fans.", "optb": "arrangement of heating stock in the furnaces.", "optc": "location of outlet ports and heating & combustion devices.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of combustible escaping uncon-sumed from the furnace, depends upon the", "opta": "air supplied and furnace temperature.", "optb": "burner design (thoroughness of mixing versus stratification).", "optc": "air preheat and the flow of gases in the furnace (mixing by induction, by acceleration or by change of direction).", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is an indirectly heated furnace.", "opta": "Open hearth furnace", "optb": "Muffle furnace", "optc": "Soaking pit", "optd": "Reheating furnace", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of an air/fuel gas preheating recuperator may be as high as __________ percent.", "opta": "50", "optb": "65", "optc": "85", "optd": "99", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a muffle furnace, the muffle", "opta": "retards the heat transfer.", "optb": "assists in temperature equalisation in the charge.", "optc": "permits the use of controlled atmosphere for the protection of stock.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is not a hearth furnace ?", "opta": "Glass tank furnace", "optb": "Open hearth furnace", "optc": "Cupola", "optd": "Reheating furnace", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An example of shaft furnace is the", "opta": "L.D. converter", "optb": "glass melting tank", "optc": "blast furnace", "optd": "soaking pit", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}